Guide to the New-York Historical Society Librarian Dorothy C. Barck Records 1921-1954 NYHS-RG 19
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society Librarian Dorothy C. Barck records
1921-1954
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 19
11.5 Linear feet in 26 document boxes and one box of cards.
The New-York Historical Society Librarian Dorothy C. Barck record group primarily contains correspondence between Barck and patrons or members of N-YHS concerning research inquiries. The correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing letters from many amateur historians and genealogists. Some correspondence relates to Barck's duties as Editor, as head of the library, and to her involvement with professional organizations of librarians and archivists. The record group also includes annual reports, forms, statistics, offers from book dealers and sellers, and logbooks of reference inquiries.
Arrangement Note
The correspondence in this series is arranged in six chronological sets, which are arranged alphabetically by correspondent within each set. Frequent or notable correspondents have been noted at the folder level, as has notable contents. The miscellaneous folders included in most of the chronological sets contain content that may overlap with the alphabetical files, so it is recommended to refer to both. As time went on, less and less incoming correspondence was kept in Barck's files and it is likely that the other half of the communication can be found in the General Correspondence files (NYHS-RG 2).
At the end of the chronological sets is topical correspondence, alphabetically arranged by subject matter. The contents of the topical folders are noted at the folder level. Some materials related to the contents of the topical folders can be found within the chronological sets, so it is recommended to consult the appropriate date range and alphabetical folder.
Following the topical folders are two groups of For Sale letters, which are loosely chronological. Frequent correspondents in this group are listed at the folder level.
At the end of the record group are three notebooks and a telephone index.
Biographical/Historical Note
Dorothy C. Barck was hired as an assistant in the library at the New-York Historical Society in 1922 by Librarian Alexander Wall. She did not have a background in librarianship, but a bachelor's degree from Vassar College and a master's in American history from Cornell.
By the early 1930s, when this record group begins, Barck had responsibility as the head of reference and research and in 1936 took over from Wall as Editor. In this capacity she managed the editorial responsibilities for the publications of the library and also the Quarterly Bulletin. She edited several publications, including Letters from John Pintard to His Daughter (1816-1833). When Charles Baker was hired as full-time Editor in 1944 Barck retained the editorial duties surrounding the Bulletin, but only for a short time. As the head of reference and research, Barck answered many research and genealogical inquiries and managed Photostat orders (a type of early copy machine).
During the late 1930s, the N-YHS underwent major construction on its building, which was not completed until 1939. While construction was underway, some of the collection was put in storage and the library was closed to the public, but Barck continued to manage the reference inquiries as best she could. In 1937, Wall became Director, a newly-created position, and the library staff increased substantially. In the early years of Barck's tenure, the staff was quite small, but when the building reopened it grew into several departments and staff members, including a curator of manuscripts, a chief of the reading room, map and print room staff, and several others. For a time, Wall managed the library as Director, but in 1942 Barck was named Librarian, taking over management of the day-to-day operations of the library. In this capacity, Barck was manager of the entire library, and the first woman to hold this position.
During World War II, Barck helped oversee the transport (and subsequent retrieval) of materials from N-YHS to safe locations. She was active in acquiring war-related materials for the collection and sent out several requests for current and older war posters, including recruitment posters. After the war she sent letters to several members of the government in order to ensure that the naval collection remained current.
Barck was very active in professional organizations during her time at N-YHS. She was a member of the Special Libraries Association (SLA), the Society of American Archivists (SAA), the American Association for State and Local History (AASLH), and others. Beyond being a member, Barck was active as a leader in these organizations. She presented at the annual SAA conference in 1951 on the presentation of archival displays at the N-YHS, the AASLH annual conference of 1948 on how reference problems were handled at the N-YHS, and was part of a panel about the magazine American Heritage at the AASLH annual meeting of 1952. Barck served as Chairman of the Museum Group of SLA, the Archives Group of SLA, the nominating committee of the AASLH, the Librarians section of the American Association of Museums, and was vice-Chairman of the New York Chapter of the Steamship Historical Society of America. Additionally, Barck was in attendance at the first annual SAA meeting and was acting-secretary/treasurer and council member when the AASLH was first established.
During Barck's time at N-YHS, the library changed drastically. Barck was an advocate for allowing youth and college-age students to use the library, and a 1948 statistic estimated that only one in twelve users was a member. In 1940, the library began to implement the Library of Congress classification system for new acquisitions, and in 1941, the curator of manuscripts Susan Lyman published a Survey of the Manuscript Collections in the New-York Historical Society. Barck also organized the microfilming of one of the largest collections at N-YHS, the American Fur Company Papers. The finished product was 37 reels, with the cost split between several cooperating libraries.
Dorothy Barck left N-YHS in 1954 after 32 years of employment. When she left she was managing seventeen staff members, the largest staff to date. She went on to become the Historic Sites Supervisor at Washington's Headquarters in Newburgh, New York, and later the librarian and editor of the New York State Historical Association in Cooperstown, New York.
(Principal sources for this note include the Dorothy C. Barck records themselves and Pamela Spence Richards's Scholars and Gentleman: The Library of the New-York Historical Society 1804-1982.)
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives).
It is unlikely that this record group is the only place where correspondence to or from Barck is present, and as the later sets of correspondence primarily include the outgoing correspondence, it may be necessary to consult the General Correspondence (NYHS-RG 2) files for additional materials.
Scope and Contents Note
The Librarian Dorothy C. Barck records primarily contain chronologically arranged sets of correspondence between Barck and patrons or members of the New-York Historical Society from the 1930s to the early 1950s.
The correspondence sets contain both incoming and outgoing letters, until the last set (1946-53), which is primarily outgoing correspondence and notes from Barck's employees. The bulk of the correspondence includes reference questions, many of which are genealogical inquiries. Also included are many letters related to Photostat orders and some personal correspondence. As Barck's role within the library changed, additional content appears. Some editorial correspondence can be found prior to 1944, and after Barck becomes Librarian in 1942, some correspondence related to hiring staff, and the acquisition of donated items and sales is present.
Many of Barck's correspondents are amateur historians, genealogists, and fellow librarians at institutions such as the American Antiquarian Society and the Library of Congress. Some of Barck's most frequent correspondents over the years are: M. V. Brewington, Bruce "The Answer Man" Chapman, Bartlett Cowdrey, Arthur C. Gerow, Richard Hyer, Rev. George B. Kinkead, John Hill Morgan, Robert Livingston Nicholson, S. H. P. Pell, Helen Wilkinson Reynolds, and Florence E. Youngs.
Materials related to Barck's many professional organizations and activities are also found throughout the collection. There are some copies of speeches given at national conferences of the American Association for State and Local History or the Society of American Archivists, in addition to mailings from these organizations and the Special Libraries Association. There is correspondence related to Barck's leadership roles in these organizations and some printed materials from the National Archives, the New Jersey College for Women, University Microfilms, and some questionnaires from institutions and library students. In the topical boxes are several folders devoted to Barck's activities with the AASLH. Also present are copies of articles and their respective notes prepared by Barck for the N-YHS's Quarterly Bulletin.
Some internal correspondence can be found throughout the files, including memos and notes from Barck's staff about research or acquisition recommendations. In the last set of correspondence nearly every outgoing letter from Barck is attached to accompanying notes from staff members, most frequently the reference librarian E. Marie Becker and the newspaper librarian Louis J. Fox.
The topical boxes contain more information related to the running of the N-YHS Library. Nearly a decade of annual reports including notes from staff members about statistics and usage can be found in the topical boxes. Forms, memos, statistics, and other materials related to the collections of the N-YHS can be found in this set.
The For Sale letter folders contain primarily incoming correspondence from book dealers and individual sellers.
The collection closes with three notebooks and a telephone index. Two of the notebooks are logs of reference inquiries assigned to N-YHS staff and the third contains correspondence answered directly by Barck. These notebooks also indicate the correspondent, the subject matter, and whether a response was written.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Booksellers and bookselling; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Librarians -- Correspondence.; Historians -- Correspondence.; Genealogists -- Correspondence.; Acquisitions (Libraries) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Libraries and booksellers; Kinkead, George Blackburn -- Correspondence; Reynolds, Helen Wilkinson -- Correspondence; New-York Historical Society. Library -- Management; Barck, Dorothy C. -- Correspondence; Brewington, M. V. (Marion Vernon), 1902-1974 -- Correspondence; Cowdrey, Mary Bartlett, 1910-1974 -- Correspondence; New-York Historical Society. Editorial Department -- Management; New-York Historical Society -- Correspondence; Youngs, Florence E. (Florence Evelyn), 1868-1950 -- Correspondence; New-York Historical Society -- Archives; Morgan, John Hill, 1870-1945 -- Correspondence
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. A (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Principal correspondents: Frank C. Ayres of the Business Historical Society concerning Barck's article for its Bulletin, and other matters.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. BA-BEC (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. BEE-BV (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  Frequent correspondents include Clarence W. Bowen and M.V. Brewington.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. C (3 folders) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4-6)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. D-E (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. F (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes correspondence with DeLancey W. Fiske about exhibitions held from May 1934 to December 1935.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. G (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  Frequent correspondent: Arthur C. Gerow.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. H (2 folders) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10-11)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. I-J (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. K (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. L (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. MC (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  Frequent correspondent: Richard C. McKay.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. M (2 folders) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5-6)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. N (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  Frequent correspondents include Captain D.W. Knox of the Office of Naval Records and Library and the New York Public Library.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. O-P (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  Frequent correspondent: S. H. P. Pell.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. Q-R (2 folders) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-10)
  Frequent correspondents include William F. Reeves and Wallace Reid. Includes correspondence with William F. Reeves about the publication of his book and the foreword he wrote for it.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. S (2 folders) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-2)
  Frequent correspondent: George A. Slater.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. T-U (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. V (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. W (2 folders) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5-6)
  Notable correspondent is Alexander J. Wall, writing Barck as he traveled in Europe, and T.R. Goodwin and others from Colonial Williamsburg regarding Barck's visit there. Frequent correspondents include Donald Wallace, Philip L. Watkins, and Stanley T. Williams.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. Y-Z (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  Frequent correspondents include Florence E. Youngs.
- 1933-1935 Correspondence. Misc. A-Z (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
- 1936 Correspondence. A (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
- 1936 Correspondence. B (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
- 1936 Correspondence. C-D (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
- 1936 Correspondence. E-G (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
- 1936 Correspondence. H (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  Frequent correspondent: Richard Hyer.
- 1936 Correspondence. J-L (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
  Frequent correspondent: George B. Kinkead, chaplain of the College of Preachers at Cathedral Close.
- 1936 Correspondence. M (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
- 1936 Correspondence. N-P (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  Frequent correspondent: Stephen H. P. Pell.
- 1936 Correspondence. Q-R (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
- 1936 Correspondence. S-V (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
- 1936 Correspondence. W-Y (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  Frequent correspondents: J. C. Webster of the Historic Sites and Monuments Board of Canada and Florence E. Youngs.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. A (2 folders) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6-7)
  Frequent correspondents: Albert "The Answer Man" Mitchell and the American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. BA-BENN (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  Frequent correspondents include Helen Baldwin and Lockwood Barr.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. BENS-BU (3 folders) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9-11)
  Frequent correspondents: Arthur D. Benson and M. V. Brewington. Includes News Bulletin for the American Immigration Conference Board dated July 1939.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. C (2 folders) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12-13)
  Frequent correspondent: William Bell Clark.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. D (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. E (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  Frequent correspondent: George Simpson Eddy.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. F (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. G (2 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4-5)
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. H (3 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6-8)
  Frequent correspondents: Read B. Harding and Richard Hyer of the Hyer Family Association for Genealogical Research.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. Ide, John Jay (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  Contains correspondence related to the publishing by N-YHS of John Jay Ide's The Portraits of John Jay, a volume in the John Divine Jones Fund series.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. I-J (2 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10-11)
  Frequent correspondents: Stuart W. Jackson and William Bridges Johnson.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. K (2 folders) (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12-13)
  Frequent correspondents: Fiske Kimball and George Blackburn Kinkead of the College of Preachers.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. L (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. M (3 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-3)
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. Morgan, John Hill (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  Includes correspondence relating to the publication by N-YHS of John Hill Morgan's Gilbert Stuart and His Pupils, a volume of the John Divine Jones Fund series.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. N (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5-6)
  Frequent correspondents: Edward P. Alexander, Director of the New York State Historical Association, Hugh M. Flick of the University of the State of New York, and Robert Livingston Nicholson. Includes a review written by Barck of the book Brooklyn Village, 1816-1834.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. O-P (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7-8)
  Frequent correspondent: Charles W. Pettit, State of Delaware, State Tax Department.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. Q-R (3 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9-11)
  Frequent correspondent: Helen Wilkinson Reynolds.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. SA-SL (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12-13)
  Frequent correspondent: Storrs Henry Seeley.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. SM-SW (2 folders) (Offsite-box 6, Folder 14-15)
  Notable correspondence: the Society of American Archivists sent materials relating to the Society's early events and activities, and to their inaugural meeting, which Barck attended; letter from Congressman Foster Stearns of New Hampshire regarding a constituent's inquiry.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. T (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
  Frequent correspondents: Kendall B. Taft and Colin Simkin of The Travelers Insurance Company.
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. U-V (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. W (2 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3-4)
- 1937-1939 Correspondence. Y-Z (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
  Frequent correspondent: Florence E. Youngs.
- 1940-1941 Correspondence. A-B (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
  Includes minutes of the February 17, 1941, Board of Trustees meeting of the American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society.
- 1940-1941 Correspondence. C-L (2 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7-8)
- 1940-1941 Correspondence. M-N (2 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9-10)
  Frequent correspondents: Captain D. W. Knox of the Office of Naval Records and Library, Navy Department; and Robert Livingston Nicholson.
- 1940-1941 Correspondence. O-P (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
- 1940-1941 Correspondence. Q-S (2 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12-13)
  Includes four Schrafft's press releases from 1941 and materials related to the events and activities of the Society of American Archivists (SAA), in particular the annual meetings.
- 1940-1941 Correspondence. T-Z (2 folders) (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14-15)
  Frequent correspondent: Captain H. A. Baldridge, Curator, United States Naval Academy.
- 1940-1941 Correspondence. Misc. A-Z (2 folders), 1939-1941 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-2)
  Includes outgoing correspondence only, primarily related to reference questions, some editing and personal correspondence.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. A (3 folders) (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3-5)
  Includes a list of "notable" acquisitions from 1943-1944 which was sent to the Board of the American Libraries Association. Frequent correspondents: Clarence S. Brigham, director of the American Antiquarian Society, and Bruce "The Answer Man" Chapman.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. BA-BL (3 folders) (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6-8)
  Frequent correspondents: Lockwood Barr and Douglas C. McMurtrie, Editor in Chief of the Bibliography of American Imprints. Includes correspondence related to the hiring of E. Marie Becker as a reference librarian.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. BO-BY (3 folders) (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9-11)
  Frequent correspondent: Rowena Morrison Buffington.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. CA-CLA (2 folders) (Offsite-box 8, Folder 12-13)
  Frequent correspondent: William Bell Clark. Includes a letter to Gerald Carson over Director Vail's signature summarizing the history and contributions of the Field Exploration Committee.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. CLE-CU (2 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-2)
  Frequent correspondent: Hayward Cleveland.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. D (3 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3-5)
  Frequent correspondents: Mrs. Lincoln A. Osborn of the Manhattan Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution and John Ross Delafield.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. Drake, PFC Robert J. (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
  Correspondence with PFC Robert J. Drake primarily about his research with and publication of the journal of John P. Bannon.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. E, 1940-1946 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7)
  Includes correspondence with Eugene M. Ettenberg of the Gallery Press concerning proofs of the bookplate for the Leonidas Westervelt Jenny Lind Collection.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. F (2 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8-9)
  Frequent correspondents: Charles Edey Fay, Stuyvesant Fish, and Ethelwyn Manning, Librarian at the Frick Art Reference Library.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. G (3 folders) (Offsite-box 9, Folder 10-12)
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. George Grady Press (Offsite-box 9, Folder 13)
  Correspondence focusing primarily on Bulletin and Annual Report publications.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. HA-HAY (2 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-2)
  Frequent correspondent: Clifford K. Shipton of Harvard University. Includes correspondence with Henry O. Havemeyer concerning his donation of papers from the Imperial Mexican Consulate during the time of Emperor Maximilian.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. HE-HY (3 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3-5)
  Frequent correspondents: Lt. j.g. H. Maxson Holloway (N-YHS Museum Curator serving in the Navy), Richard J. Hooker, and Herbert Barber Howe (concerning his gift of the John Moffat Howe papers and other items).
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. I-J (2 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6-7)
  Frequent correspondents: Frances Irvin, and Stuart Wells Jackson.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. KA-KI (2 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8-9)
  Frequent correspondent: Rev. George B. Kinkead. Includes reference inquiries from Pvt. Lincoln Kirstein.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. KL-KU (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10)
  Frequent correspondents: Mary L. Knowlton and her daughters Dorothy, Florence and Jean.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. LA-LE (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11)
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. LI-LY (2 folders) (Offsite-box 10, Folder 12-13)
  Frequent correspondents: many different people associated with the Library of Congress, and Stewart McClelland and others from Lincoln Memorial University.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. MC-MAY (2 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-2)
  Frequent correspondents: Commander L. McCormick-Goodhart, Thomas Ollive Mabbott, Mrs. Charles Lester Marlatt, and William D. Hoyt, Jr of the Maryland Historical Society.
- 1942-1945 Correspondence. ME-MI (2 folders), 1941-1945 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3-4)
  Frequent correspondent: Jesse Merritt, County Historian in Nassau County.